hey what's up guys my name is Aero and
today we're going to talk about linking
so what is linking what does the C++
Linker actually do linking is a process
that we go through when we go from our
source C++ files to our actual
executable binary so the first stage is
actually compiling our source files and
I actually made an entire video on that
so go check that out Link in the
description below once we've compiled
our files we need to go through a
process called linking now the primary
focus of linking is to find where each
symbol and function is and Link them
together remember each file is compiled
into a separate object file as a
translation unit and they have no
relation to each other those files can't
actually interact so if we decide to
split our program across multiple C++
files which is of course very common we
need a way to actually link those files
together into one program and that is
the primary purpose of what the Linker
does even if you don't have functions in
external files like for example you've
written your entire program in one file
the application still needs to know
where the entry point is so in other
words where the main function is so that
when you actually run your application
the C runtime Library can say hey here's
the main function I'm going to jump
there and start executing code from
there and that is effectively what
starts your application so it still
needs to link the main function and
everything like that even if you don't
have other files the best way to explain
this is by showing some examples so
let's jump over and take a look so here
in Visual Studio we've got a very simple
project that just contains one source
file math. cppp and inside there we have
two functions log and multiply the
multiply function actually calls the log
function prints out the word multiply to
the console and then returns a * B
pretty simple stuff however this isn't
an actual application since of course it
doesn't contain a main function the
first thing that you have to realize is
that there are those two stages of
compilation right there's compiling and
there's linking and there's actually a
way that you can differentiate between
the two in visual studio if you press
contrl F7 or if you press the compile
button only compilation will happen no
linking will ever happen however if you
build your project or if you hit F5 to
run your project it will actually
compile and then link so if I just hit
contrl F7 you'll see that I actually get
no errors everything's fine because the
compilation was successful it generated
that math. obj file the object file and
everything's great however if I right
click on my project and hit build you'll
see that I actually get a linking error
entry point must be defined and again
that's because I'm missing my entry
point my main function so because our
compilation is divided into those two
stages compiling and linking we actually
get different types of error messages
associated with each stage if I make a
syntax error for example which of course
is something the compiler has to deal
with if I compile my code you'll see
that it tells me that I actually get an
error which is called c2143 and then it
says syntax error of course so this is
the error code for this type of error
and you'll note that it actually starts
with the letter c this tells us that
it's an error that occurred in the
compiling stage if I fix that and then
build my entire project you'll see the
error code listed here begins with the
letters l and K which of course stands
for link and it even tells us over here
that this happened during the link stage
it's really important that you know what
kind of error you get whether it's a
compiling error or a linking error
because of course you need to know that
so that you can fix it properly so in
this case we get an error which tells us
the entry point must be defined again
that is because we are compiling this as
an application if we go to our
properties and we take a look at what
configuration type we have set here
you'll see it is set to application. exe
and every exe file has to have some kind
of entry point if we go over here into
the Linker settings and into advanced
you'll actually see that we can specify
a custom entry point the entry point
doesn't have to be the main function
there just has to be an entry point now
normally it is the main function and for
pretty much anything you do it probably
will be the main function but just so
you know entry point doesn't necessarily
have to be a function called main it can
be really anything so if we back out of
here and actually write that main
function I'll just write int Main
and then I'll build my project again
you'll see that we no longer get that
linking error and that we were
successfully able to generate that exe
file all right so now that we've
established that let's go ahead and
print out the value of that multiply
function so we'll multiply 5 and 8
together so what we should see is this
message being logged and then the value
40 being printed let's also add a c in.
getet so that our console doesn't close
close immediately then I'll just click
on this local Windows debugger button to
run this as you can see we get multiply
and 40 so our application seems to be
running correctly great now suppose I
had these in multiple files for example
this log doesn't really need to be in
this math file because of course this
just logs a message so why don't I have
a separate file that actually contains
all of my logging related functions I'm
going to right click on source files and
add a new C++ file called log CPP and
then I'll click add I'm going to grab
that log function from here and move it
into my log. CPP file if I go back to
math. CPP and try and compile this code
I'll get an error and you'll know that
this is a compile error because the
error code begins with the letter c
telling me that log is not found because
this file has no knowledge that a
function called log exists at all so
we'll go ahead and grab this first line
of the log function which is the
signature and we'll add this so that we
have a declaration of the log function
in this math. zppp file I'll hit contr
F7 and you can see that compiling worked
now let's go ahead and build our entire
project we get several errors here
compile errors telling us the C out is
not found because we need to actually
include IO
stream once we've done that let's build
our entire project all right great it
seemed to work successfully now let's
take a look at one type of linking error
that we might get this one's called
unresolved external symbol and this is
what happens when the Linker can't find
something that it needs so we'll go back
over here and in the log file I'm going
to change this to say something else for
example I'm just going to add an R here
so that we say logger if I go back to
math. CPP I've still left my declaration
as log so it still does expect the
function to be called log so this file
will still compile of course because
this does no linking so all it's doing
is checking to make sure everything here
compiles correctly it believes that
there is a log function somewhere but
it's going to be the job of the linking
stage to actually find that log function
so if I build my entire project now
you'll see we actually get an error this
is is a linking error because you can
see that it begins with the Ln K letters
and the error says unresolved external
symbol now it tells us exactly what
symbol is missing it's that log function
it even tells us where we reference it
that we're referencing it in a function
called multiply so here it is in
multiply we're calling log and it cannot
actually find which function to link it
to so of course it has to give us an
error because when we land on that code
at runtime what is it supposed to do
when it tries to call the log function
it doesn't know where the log function
is now if I go over here and I comment
out this log function so that we
actually never call it if I try and
build this we get no errors the reason
this happens is because I never call the
log function so the Linker doesn't have
to link this function call to actually
call the log function because we never
called The Log function another
interesting note is that if I do call
the log function here on multiply
however I comment this line out so that
I never call multiply which in turn
never calls log if I build my project
now you'll see that I still get a
linking error and you might be like what
but why is that happening I'm not
calling multiply anywhere why is it
complaining about a linking error
shouldn't it have just removed the
function entirely since it's essentially
dead code that's never used wrong
because whilst we're not using the
multiply function in this file we
actually could technically use it in
another file and so the Linker does
actually need to link that if we could
somehow tell the compiler that hey this
function multiply I'm only ever going to
use it inside this file then of course
we could remove that linking necessity
since if multiply is never called it
never needs to call log oh wait there is
a way we could do that if we come over
here and write the word static in front
of multiply that basically means that
this multiply function is only declared
for this translation unit which is this
math. CPP file in our case and since
multiply is never called inside this
file if I build we won't get any linking
errors if I bring back my comment though
and then I build of course we will get a
linking error in this case we actually
ended up modifying the name of the
function however it's not just the name
of the function that matters if I bring
back this function I'll call it log
again I'll build my project we won't get
any errors but then I for example change
the return type to be int and then I'll
just return zero or something like that
if I build my project now you'll see
that we get an error because in math.
CPP we specify that this log function
was a void function and so because of
that it's going to look for a function
called log that returns void and also
takes in this one parameter if I go back
to log and I might change this back to
void get rid of this return zero and
build it everything works fine but then
I might add another parameter for
example the level if I now build this
we'll get a linking error once again
because the log function that it expects
does not have another parameter you'll
see if we go down here into linking
error message it actually expects a
function which returns void which has
this calling convention it's called log
and it has to have just one parameter
which is a const Shar pointer that's it
if it cannot find exactly that then
you're going to get a linking error
let's go back over here to our log file
and just remove this level so that our
program works again and if I build it of
course we shouldn't get any linking
errors great okay so the other type of
linking error that's pretty common is
when we have duplicate symbols so in
other words we have functions or
variables which have the same name and
the same signature so two identically
named functions which have the same
return value and the same parameters if
that happens we're trouble the reason
we're in trouble is because the Linker
doesn't know which one to link to it's
ambiguous so back in our code if I was
for example to write another version of
this function so I'll just literally
copy and paste this function and try and
build my code you'll note that we
actually get a compile error because
this already has a body and the compiler
can kind of tell us that yeah okay since
I'm compiling this file I can obviously
see that you've made a mistake this cist
isn't valid so this is an example of
having duplicate symbols where the
compiler can actually save us because
this all happens in one file and no
linking actually needs to happen to see
that we've got an error however if I was
to move this into a different file for
example I'll move it back into our math
file right over here so we still have
our declaration I can leave that there
that's fine that's just a declaration we
only have one definition of log in this
file so it's not going to give us a
compiling error if I hit contrl F7 just
to compile this you can see it's totally
fine but now if I build we get a linking
error and you can see that the one we
get it tells us that we have this log
function already defined in log. obj one
or more multiply defined symbols found
so in this case the Linker doesn't know
which log function to link to does it
link to the one in math. CPP or does it
link to the one in log. CPP it doesn't
know now you might think that this type
of error is not something that would
happen often and that you're smarter
than that however this can creep up on
you so I'll show you a few ways as to
how that can happen all right firstly
let's just remove this extra log
definition we have here so that our
project builds successfully now let's
create a header file I'm going right
click on header files select add new
item it's going to be a header file I'm
going to call this file log. and click
add now inside here I'm going to grab
this log function and make sure that I'm
declaring it inside this header file if
I go back to log CPP I'll write some
kind of other function for example init
log that's just going to call the log
function and say that it's initialized
the log of course if we try and compile
now we're going to get an error because
we need that log function so I'll
include
log back over here in math. CPP instead
of having this declaration here I'm also
going to include
log so great we're calling the log
function from both the multiply function
inside the math. zvp file as well as the
init log inside the log. CPP file it
doesn't really matter that I'm not
calling this function so don't worry
about that I'm just going to build my
project okay check this out I get an
error telling me that log is already
defined in log. objs so we get a one or
more multiply defined symbols found so
we're getting a duplicate symbol error
message however you can see that I've
really only got one definition of log
it's inside this log Doh file why is it
complaining about multiple symbols now
this comes back to how the include
statement Works remember when we include
a header file we're just taking the
contents of that header file and putting
it where our include statement is so
what's actually happened is it's taken
this log function popped it over here
like so into log. CVP and then also over
here and now you can see that we of
course do have two log functions so how
do we fix this well we've got a few
options here if we undo all of this so
that we're including log again we could
mark this log function as static that
means that the linking that should
happen to this log function should only
be internal which means that this log
function when it gets included into log.
CPP and math. CPP is going to be just
internal to this file kind of like what
we did with multiply so basically log
and math will have their own versions of
this function called log and it won't be
visible to any other object files so if
we just just compile this now you'll see
that we won't get any linking errors
another thing that we could do to this
is make it inline of course inline just
means that it's going to take our actual
function body and replace the call with
it so in this case this log initialized
log would just
become
that so if we were to do something like
that and build you'll see that we get no
errors either now there's one other way
that we could fix this and that's
probably what I would do in this
situation and that is just move the
definition of this into one translation
unit because right now what's happening
is this log function is being included
in two translation units log. CPP and
math. zpp that's what's causing the
error in the first place so we can move
it into a third translation unit or we
could put this log definition into one
of these existing translation units
since this function is called log and
it's related to logging I'm actually
going to put it into log. cppp so I'll
grab this function I'll copy it into
log. CPP I'll get rid of the inline and
then I'll come back to my log. and just
leave the Declaration here again without
the inline of course so now this t a
file just has the Declaration for log
the actual function to link to is
included inside log. CPP once in one
translation unit in our project and then
main will call that so if I build this
we get no linking errors and our project
was able to be linked successfully so
that's it that's pretty much a quick
crash course on linking and how linking
Works remember at the end of the day the
Linker needs to take all of our object
files that were generated during
compilation and Link them all together
it will also pull in any other libraries
that we may may be using for example the
C runtime Library the C++ standard
Library our platform apis if necessary
and a whole lot of other stuff it's very
common to be linking from many different
places there's also different types of
linking we have static linking and we
have Dynamic linking but I'll save that
for another video anyway thanks for
watching I hope you enjoyed this video
if you have any other questions just
leave them in the comment section below
and I'll try my best to answer them be
sure to follow me on Twitter and
Instagram and if you really like this
video you can support me on patreon
that'll help me make more of these
videos and by by doing so you'll also
get access to early drafts of videos and
be involved in the planning process but
as always I'll see you guys next time
goodbye Voom